Guide to the Randolph Somerville Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Randolph Somerville Papers
[ca. 1915]-1958.
Somerville, Randolph, 1891-1958.
29.5 linear ft. (63 document boxes & 1 flat box).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4079354
Biographical Note
Director, actor, professor of dramatic art at New York University, and organizer and director of the Washington Square Players Repertory Company.
Scope and Content
Papers, promptbooks, photographs, lecture notes, correspondence, and theatrical files of Somerville. Included are materials from the Washington Square Players and Duke's Oak Theatre in Cooperstown, N.Y.
Arrangement
Selectively cataloged; remainder arranged.
Subjects
Duke's Oak Theatre (Cooperstown, N.Y.); New York University--Faculty.; Washington Square Players (New York, N.Y.); Anglin, Margaret, 1876-1958.; Barrie, J. M. (James Matthew), 1860-1937.; Benedict, Ruth, 1887-1948.; Booth, Edwin, 1833-1893.; Bragdon, Claude Fayette, 1866-1946.; Digges, Dudley, 1879-1947.; Dunsany, Beatrice.; Dunsany, Edward John Moreton Drax Plunkett, Baron, 1878-1957.; Fiske, Harrison Grey, 1861-1942.; Frohman, Daniel, 1851-1940.; Geddes, Norman Bel, 1893-1958.; Howard, Leslie, 1893-1943.; Huston, Walter, 1884-1950.; Kane, Whitford, 1882-1956.; Marlowe, Julia, 1865-1950.; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953.; Pinero, Arthur Wing, Sir, 1855-1934.; Rice, Elmer, 1892-1967.; Sothern, E. H. (Edward Hugh), 1859-1933.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Taras, John.; Taylor, Laurette, 1884-1946.; Thorndike, Sybil, Dame, 1882-1976.; Tree, Herbert Beerbohm, Sir, 1853-1917.; Winter, William, 1836-1917.; Wycherly, Margaret, 1881-1956.; Zorina, Vera.; Theater--New York (State)--New York.; Theater--New York (State)--Cooperstown.; Drama--Study and teaching.; Notes.; Photographs.; Photoprints.; Playbills.; Plays.; Posters.; Prints.; Prompt books.; Scrapbooks.; Scripts.; Actors.; Actresses.; College teachers.; Dramatists.; Theatrical producers and directors.; Theatrical managers.
Access Restrictions
Available for faculty, students, and researchers engaged in scholarly or publication projects.
Boxes 6-62 are located off-site and require advance notice of intent to use.
Acquisition
1959 M-59 Estate of Randolph Somerville Bequest
Bequest of Randolph Somerville, 1959.
- Series I: John Somerville Papers
  - Cataloged Correspondence and Documents (Box 1-5)
  - Photographs (Box 6)
  - Negatives and Financial Papers (Box 7)
  - Lecture Notes, Playbills, Clippings, etc. (Box 8-12)
  - Shakespeare (Box 13-15)
  - Washington Square Players and Duke's Oak Theatre (Box 16-17)
  - 19th Century Players' Scripts and Prompt Books (Box 18-19)
  - Books from Somerville's Library, with notes (Box 20-27)
  - Books from Somerville's library, inscribed (Box 28-31)
  - Books from the library of Louis Calvert (Box 32-38)
  - Somerville's Prompt Books (Box 39-62)
  - Scrapbook of Clippings and Press, 1919-1927 (Box 63)
  - Actors are Born and Not Made Manuscript, 1955 (Box 64)
  - Macbeth Performance-- Audio Reel and CD, 1957 (Box 64)
    (starring Somerville and Marian Primont)
  - Photographs (Box 64)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1958 (Box 64)
    (regarding Somerville's retirement from new York University)
  - Student Papers by Antonio Valentin, 1960 (Box 64)